<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stromberg Labs</title>
    <link>/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Stromberg Labs</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 01:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Water Table</title>
      <link>/portfolio/water_table/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/portfolio/water_table/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;My daughter loves to play with water, but gets more of a kick out of running water, so I went looking for a water table with a pump. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to find much, only ones with manual pumps which seemed out of her reach at that age, so I tried making my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;finished-product&#34;&gt;Finished Product&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;img-responsive center-block&#34; src=&#34;/img/water_table.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 300px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/water_table_bottom.JPG&#34;&gt;A plastic bin to hold the water and the pump&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/water_table_top.JPG&#34;&gt;Same size bin, half the height for the top&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/water_table_pump.JPG&#34;&gt;A fountain pump&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; PVC tubing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A threaded connector for the pump to the PVC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;assembly&#34;&gt;Assembly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assembly is pretty straightforward&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut a hole in the bottom bin, just wide enough for the pump plug to run through it, just below the lowest point of the top tray.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut a hole in the top tray where you want the PVC to come up through. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about making this exact, since you&amp;rsquo;ll want some water to flow back down, but start small.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get creative with the PVC tubing, drill some holes, add some connectors, but don&amp;rsquo;t glue it together, since you&amp;rsquo;ll want to be able to take it apart. When it&amp;rsquo;s dry fitted it still holds together well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll have to adjust the size of the whole in the top tray so that it keeps some water, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t pump out the bottom entirely. I was surprised that this only took us a couple of hours to build and didn&amp;rsquo;t see anything like this on the internet yet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NFL In Game Win Probability</title>
      <link>/portfolio/igwip_nfl/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/portfolio/igwip_nfl/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I did the NBA in game win probability, but I really wanted to do one for the NFL,
so here we are. This is all based on the great explanations at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pro-football-reference.com/about/win_prob.htm&#34;&gt;Pro Football Reference&lt;/a&gt;, with some
more intermediate graphics and steps that helped me understand it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-game-probability&#34;&gt;In Game Probability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I wanted to do was to recreate the win probability laid out
that the score is a normal random variable, centered around the current point
differential. The sigma of the curve decreases linearly as the game progresses,
so the curve gets more pointy until the very end of the game, where there is
only a single outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;select id=&#34;game-picker&#34;&gt;
  &lt;option value=&#34;1&#34;&gt;WAS vs CIN, 10/30/2016 (Tie Game)&lt;/option&gt;
  &lt;option value=&#34;0&#34;&gt;MIN vs CLE, 9/13/2009 (Just a Game)&lt;/option&gt;
  &lt;option value=&#34;2&#34;&gt;BAL vs MIN, 12/8/2013 (Wild Last Two Minutes)&lt;/option&gt;
  &lt;option value=&#34;3&#34;&gt;DET vs PHI, 12/8/2013 (Snow Bowl!)&lt;/option&gt;
&lt;/select&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;canvas id=&#34;chart&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
  &lt;div style=&#34;color: #999999;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div style=&#34;margin-top: 10px;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;col-md-6 text-center&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;game-time&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;col-md-6 text-center&#34;&gt;Lead: &lt;span id=&#34;lead&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;col-md-4 text-center&#34;&gt;Win: &lt;span id=&#34;percent-win&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;%&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;col-md-4 text-center&#34;&gt;Tie: &lt;span id=&#34;percent-tie&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;%&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;col-md-4 text-center&#34;&gt;Loss: &lt;span id=&#34;percent-loss&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;%&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;input id=&#34;slider&#34; type=&#34;range&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;script src=&#34;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/Chart.js/2.7.0/Chart.bundle.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&#34;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/decimal.js/7.2.4/decimal.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script src=&#34;/js/igwip_nfl.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty fun, right? The data for this comes from nflscrapR author &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/maxhorowitz/nflplaybyplay2009to2016&#34;&gt;Max Horowitz&amp;rsquo;s Kaggle page&lt;/a&gt;. Without his
work, I don&amp;rsquo;t believe there would be any good free data on the NFL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;including-expected-points&#34;&gt;Including Expected Points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous win probabilities don&amp;rsquo;t take into account the current state of
players on the field. If you are up by two, but the opposing team is at your 30
yard line with 10 seconds left, they&amp;rsquo;ll probably kick a field goal and go home.
Right now this model doesn&amp;rsquo;t account for this, but we can if we included the
expected number of points for their current drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to get to this eventually ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-reading&#34;&gt;Additional Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pro-football-reference.com/about/win_prob.htm&#34;&gt;PFR In Game Win Probability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/maxhorowitz/nflplaybyplay2009to2016&#34;&gt;NFL Play by Play Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.footballperspective.com/quarter-by-quarter-team-win-probability-added/&#34;&gt;Quarter By Quarter Probability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cmusportsanalytics.com/nfl-expected-points-nflscrapr-part-2-multinomial-logistic-regression/&#34;&gt;CMU Expected Points Model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image for this post can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/search/photos/american-football?photo=iezcEpGuYdE&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halloween Candy Survey</title>
      <link>/portfolio/halloween/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 18:25:22 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/portfolio/halloween/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;So back when we first moved into our neighborhood, the folks next door warned us that we needed to buy a lot of candy for Halloween, at least several hundred pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went to the store I found that I had no idea what to buy. What kind of candy do kids even like? I bought a bunch of variety packs and brought them home. The day before Halloween I got the idea I should count the candy before and after, so I would know what kids actually wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the candy is in a bowl, kids get to pick &amp;ldquo;any one they want&amp;rdquo;, a phrase which also implied quantity that they get to pick.
Periodically I&amp;rsquo;ll dump the bowl back into the collection of all the candy, stir it up and fill the bowl again to try and maintain availability of each type of candy for as long as possible.
Sometime when the night starts to die down I do another recount of the candy, after that I give away generous amounts to roving bands of high schoolers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raw data is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gLhE7yLB8ZK5EA02RhdbpDEBh3joMo1Tl7OSOt0tluY/view&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Generally the big take away that I can discern is that kids love Skittles.
It might have something to do with it&amp;rsquo;s relative rarity of non chocolatey candy in variety packs, which I think leads to relatively rarity in the neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;yearly-notes&#34;&gt;Yearly Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2012&#34;&gt;2012&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skittles were the big winner, kids don&amp;rsquo;t generally choose chocolatey candy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2014&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we did a prediction to see exactly how much candy we should stock but didn&amp;rsquo;t give ourselves any buffer, so we ended up &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; completely running out! This left us with no good way to see preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2015&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chocolatey candy is slowly closing on the non chocolately candy, but Skittles continue to have a good run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2016&#34;&gt;2016&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lowest turnout year yet! I guess rainy Monday nights aren&amp;rsquo;t good for trick or treating. Interestingly chocolatey candy preference is slowly drawing even with non chocolatey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image for this post can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/lW25Zxpkln8&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NBA In Game Win Probability</title>
      <link>/portfolio/igwip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 18:25:22 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/portfolio/igwip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;//cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.1/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS_CHTML&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear with me for a second. I&amp;rsquo;ve get pretty stressed out when watching the Denver Broncos play. Part of my routine involves finding the in game win probability chart so that I know when I should just walk away from the game (good or bad). I also always have trouble finding these charts online, a couple of these sites like Advanced NFL Stats have slowly stopped or broken down over the years. So I figure I should make one myself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is right around the time that the Warriors were on their run for a second title with Steph Curry, so I thought I would start with basketball first. It seems a lot more straightforward because there are a lot more scoring events and the data was much much easier to get my hands on, thanks to Michael Beuoy for pointing me in the right spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first approach is to look back at previous situations and find out how likely you were to win in that situation. The &amp;ldquo;situation&amp;rdquo; was defined by what the difference in score was and the time remaining (aligned to 10 second bins). This produced results which seemed pretty good. Someday I&amp;rsquo;ll ressurect them and see if I can make some charts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second approach was to use a Logit GLM to fit a variety of data. I included home vs away, score differential, whether or not you currently possess the ball, and percentage of the game which had been completed. After my wife showed me that I should use the logit and how to convert that set of constants into a formula that produces a probability, we got this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$y = e^{-(0.2775 - 0.4483 \cdot A + 0.3208 \cdot T \cdot S + 0.2894 \cdot P)}$$
$$Probability = 1 / (1 + y)$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A = 1 if you are the away team, 0 if you are the home team.&lt;br /&gt;
T = Percentage of time remaining, from 0 to 1.&lt;br /&gt;
S = Score differential, your team&amp;rsquo;s score - the other team.&lt;br /&gt;
P = 1 if you possess the ball, 0 if you don&amp;rsquo;t possess the ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also tried some variations where ignore possession and produced some nice 3D plots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/igwip.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Example image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future iterations I hope to wire up a website that will produce these charts on demand, for past games or games which are currently being played. Some improvements I&amp;rsquo;d like to make eventually are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overtime - Right now I don&amp;rsquo;t include any overtime states in the model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;End Game - The model doesn&amp;rsquo;t take into account that if you have possession, are leading, and there is &amp;lt; $SHOT_CLOCK_TIME remaining, then you&amp;rsquo;ve basically won. The model underestimates your chances of winning in these scenarios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On demand charts for past games and currently active games.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also going to eventually take a crack at doing this for the NFL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preview image for this post can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/zjEsQhDD39I&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m just a person, doing things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>